A Register of the Vladimir Sergeevich Khitrovo Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vladimir Sergeevich Khitrovo Papers
1910-1967
2008C49
Hoover Institution Archives
2 microfilm reels (0.3 linear feet)
These papers contain the correspondence and writings of Vladimir Sergeevich Khitrovo, a graduate of the Pazheskii korpus and participant of World War I and member of the White Army
Khitrovo, Vladimir Sergeevich
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Full collection is available on microfilm
Location of Original Materials
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1891 Born, Russia
1910 Graduated, Pazheskii korpus
1918 Officer in General Kirpichev's Kievskaia dobrovol'cheskaia druzhina
1919 Officer in Svodno-gvardeiskii polk Vooruzhennykh sil iuga Rossii
1920 Chief of the Russian press bureau in Constantinople
1968 February 24 Died, Paris, France
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers contain the correspondence and writings of Vladimir Sergeevich Khitrovo, a graduate of the Pazheskii korpus and participant of World War I and member of the White Army. In emigration, Khitrovo was active in the alumni association of the Pazheskii korpus, the Soiuz pazhei, which is reflected in a number of organizational files of this association, including bylaws, correspondence, and lists of members within the Subject file. Of particular interest is Khitrovo's unpublished memoir of World War I, "Vospominaniia i materialy dlia istorii. Leib-gvardii konnaia artilleriia. Chast' II-aia. Voina 1914-1917. Pokhod v vostochnuiu Prussiiu," which include numerous original photographs.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, Subject file, and Photographs
Biography
Vladimir Sergeevich Khitrovo, born in 1891, graduated from the Pazheskii korpus in 1910 and participated in World War I. During the Civil War in 1918 he enlisted in the White Army, serving as an officer in General Lev N. Kirpichev’s Kievskaia dobrovol’cheskaia druzhina; the following year he transferred to the Svodno-gvardeiskii polk Vooruzhennykh sil iuga Rossii. Having been evacuated from Novorossiisk, Khitrovo became chief of the Russian press bureau in Constantinople and subsequently immigrated to France. He was active in the alumni association of the Pazheskii korpus and the Soiuz pazhei. He was a contributor to the journal Voennaia byl’ and authored an unpublished memoir of World War I, “Vospominaniia i materialy dlia istorii. Leib-gvardii konnaia artilleriia. Chast’ II-aia. Voina 1914-1917. Pokhod v vostochnuiu Prussiiu.”
Born in Stanitsa Piatiizbianskaia, Russia, on September 10, 1878,to a traditional Cossack family, he embarked on a military career, graduating from the Donskoi kadetskii korpus in 1896 and the Mikhailovskoe artilleriiskoe uchilishche in 1898. He served in the Twenty-first Don Cossack battery and completed the Nikolaevskaia akademiia general’nogo shtaba in 1908. In 1918, he was a commanding officer in the Don Cossack uprising; that same year he was elevated to the rank of major general and commanding officer of the Don Cossack Army.
Vladimir S. Khitrovo died on February 24, 1968, in Grasse, France
Pazheskii Ego Imperatorskogo Velichestva korpus.; Photographs.; Russia. Armiia. Konnaia artilleriia.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Biographical File, 1918-1920. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Military orders, receipts. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Military orders, 1919 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Receipts, 1918-1920 (Folder 1: 2)
- Correspondence, 1939-1965.
  General note
  See also Subject file/Soiuz pazhei/Correspondence
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Boris Vladimirovich, Grand Duke, 1939 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Golubev, Mikhail Vasil'evich, 1964 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
  - Pozdnyshev, Sergei Dimitrievich, 1963-1965. (Folder 1: 5)
    Includes clippings on the 50th anniversary of World War I
  - Skriabin, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich, 1952-1961 (Folder 1: 6)
- Speeches and Writings, 1931-1939 and undated.
  Articles, monograph, notes, arranged chronologically by title
  - General - Notes, 1931-1939 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - "Vospominaniia i materialy dlia istorii. Leib-gvardii konnaia artilleriia. Chast' II-aia. Voina 1914-1917. Pokhod v vostochnuiu Prussiiu,", undated. (Folder 1: 8)
    Typescript. Includes original prints
  - "Russkaia artilleriia v velikuiu voinu,", undated. (Folder 1: 9)
    Typescript and holograph. Includes "Artilleriia v velikuiu voinu," Russkii invalid, 20 July, 1939. Printed copy
- Subject File, 1910-1967 and undated.
  Announcements, articles, brochures, by-laws, circulars, clippings, correspondence, inventories, lists, orders, programs, receipts, tickets, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Desnitskaia, Ekaterina Ivanovna, undated. (Folder 1: 10)
    Includes newspaper clippings
  - Leib-gvardii Finliandskii polk, 1961 and undated. (Folder 1: 10)
  - Soiuz pazhei, 1910-1967 and undated
    - General
      - Anniversary celebrations, 1935-1952. (Folder 1: 11)
        Includes circulars
      - Memorial icon, Belgrade, 1933 and undated. (Folder 1: 12)
        Includes announcement and donation form
    - Bylaws, 1921-1933. (Folder 1: 13)
      Typescript and printed copies
    - Concert program, 1926. (Box-folder 2: 1)
      Printed copy
    - Correspondence, 1930-1967 and undated (Folder 2: 2)
    - Lists of members
      - Deceased, undated (Folder 2: 3)
      - General, 1910-1966 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
      - Graduates, undated lists of graduating classes from 1903 to 1914 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Memoirs, 1954-1955 and undated. (Folder 2: 6)
      Holographs
    - Menu, 1952. (Folder 2: 7)
    - Museum file, 1939-1956. (Folder 2: 8)
      Includes brochure, circular and partial inventory of Musee des pages in Paris, France
    - Opoveshchenie soiuza pazhei, 1938 and undated. (Folder 2: 9)
      Printed copy and typescript
    - Orders, undated typescript copies of orders dated, 1903-1917 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Printed matter
      - General, undated (Folder 2: 11)
      - Clippings, 1958-1965 and undated (Folder 2: 12)
      - "Imperator Pavel I Petrovich,", undated. (Folder 2: 13)
        Typescript. Includes related notes
      - "Iubileinye dni,", 1960. (Folder 2: 14)
        Typescript
      - "Pazheskii Ego Velichestva korpus, 1802-1952,", undated. (Folder 2: 15)
    - Receipts, 1929-1965 and undated (Folder 2: 16)
    - Tickets for the Bal des Pages, 1924-1939 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Vuich Iurii, 1938. (Folder 2: 18)
      Carbon copy of correspondence regarding his death
    - Miscellany, 1939 and undated. (Folder 2: 19)
      Includes 175th anniversary ribbon
  - Zakharchenko-Shul'ts, Mariia Vladislavovna, undated. (Folder 2: 20)
    Typescripts
- Photographs, undated. (Folder 2: 21)
  One negative and one print depicting banners